Finding Aid for the William Giles Harding Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
William Giles Harding Papers
1827-1872
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0189
.42 linear feet
Biography/History
William Giles Harding [1808-1886] was born near Nashville and attended the University of Nashville; the American Literary, Scientific, and Military Academy in Middletown, Connecticut; and, studied law in Litchfield, Connecticut.
William Giles Harding married Elizabeth Irwin McGavock in 1840 after the death of his first wife. He lived first at Stone’s River Farm, where his son John later lived, and then at the 3500-acre Belle Meade Plantation, where he raised cashmere goats and racehorses. He transformed the Federal style house his father built into the Greek Revival mansion that stands today.
At the beginning of the American Civil War he served as a General in the Tennessee militia. In 1862 he was imprisoned for six months by federal troops as a political prisoner, for supporting the Confederate rebellion, and sent to Detroit and Fort Mackinaw, Michigan. During his absence, his wife was left to manage Belle Meade Plantation. During the war, his plantation was used as a headquarters for the Union Army.
After the war, Belle Meade became one of the best thoroughbred breeding farms in the country.
Mrs. M. G. Buckner donated the original letters to Special Collections. Ridley Wills deposited some typed transcripts of the letters with genealogical footnotes in 1985.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear feet collection is divided into three series:
Series I includes original, handwritten general correspondence sent to William Giles Harding primarily from Matthew Fontaine Maury, 1827-1872. The letters discuss Agricultural and Meterological Societies, importation of Llamas and Alpacas from South America to Tennessee, the Civil War, and politics. It also includes an address by Matthew Fontaine Maury before the National Agricultural Association, miscellaneous notes, and typed transcripts to selected letters. The series is arranged chronologically containing 28 file folders.
Series II includes original handwritten family correspondence from William Giles Harding’s wife Elizabeth I. McGavock Harding; daughter, Selene; daughter-in-law, Maggie; servant, Susanna; sister-in-law, Mary McGavock Southall; nephew, Randal McGavock Southall; and, friends beginning in 1860 and continuing while he was in prison during the American Civil War and ending in1867. The letters chronicle family life in Nashville during the Union occupation. There are typed transcripts for selected letters, and some typed transcripts with footnotes. The series is arranged chronologically in 22 file folders, and includes two bound volumes of the same letters.
Series III contains two photographs, in two file folders.
- Series I - General – 28 file folders
  - Correspondence – Incoming
    - from Sam Houston, February 6, 1827
    - from G. E. Candway, October 7, 1827
    - from Matthew Fontaine Maury, November 20, 1859
    - to George G. Hobson from Matthew Fontaine Maury, November 25, 1959
    - to Matthew Fontaine Maury from George G. Hobson, November 29, 1859
    - to George G. Hobson from Matthew Fontaine Maury, November 30, 1859
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, December 19, 1859
    - to John R. Clay from Matthew Fontaine Maury, December 19, 1859
    - to Matthew Fontaine Maury from George G. Hobson, January 11, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, January 13, 1860
    - to Matthew Fontaine Maury from George G. Hobson, May 7, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, May 8, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, July 12, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, July 30, 1860
    - to Matthew Fontaine Maury from J. Randolph Clay, September 14, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, September 27, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, October 24, 1860
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, December 20, 1860
    - to ‘my dear sir’ from Matthew Fontaine Maury, July 3, 1861
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, October 9, 1861
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, November 24, 1861
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, December 11, 1861
    - to ‘my dear uncle’ from D. H. Maury, January 4, 1862
    - to Harding from Matthew Fontaine Maury, January 5, 1862
    - to W. H. Jackson from Matthew Fontaine Maury With newspaper clipping, March 26, 1872
    - to W. H. Jackson from Matthew Fontaine Maury, April 17, 1872
    - to W. H. Jackson from Matthew Fontaine Maury, April 29, 1872
    - to W. H. Jackson from Matthew Fontaine Maury, September 15
  - Address
    - Matthew Fontaine Maury before the National Agricultural Association, St. Louis, Missouri, May 27, 1872
  - Miscellaneous Notes
  - Transcripts – from Incoming Correspondence [selected]
    - February 6,1827
    - October 7, 1827
    - December 19, 1859
    - December 20, 1860
    - December 11, 1861
    - January 4, 1862
    - March 26, 1872
    - April 17, 1872
    - April 29, 1872
- Series II – Family Letters – 22 file folders
  - Correspondence – Outgoing
    - to his wife, Elizabeth, September 24, 1862
    - to daughter from mother, July 5, 1867
  - Correspondence – Incoming
    - from wife, Elizabeth, March 30, 1860
    - from wife, Elizabeth, April 27, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 2, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 6, 1862
    - from daughter, Selene, and from wife, May 8, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 11, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 15, 1862
    - from William Hague and his wife, Elizabeth, May 18, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 21, 1862
    - from nephew, Randal M. Southall, May 23, 1862
    - from daughter, Selene, and from wife, Elizabeth, May 25, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 26, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, May 31, 1862
    - from daughter, Selene, June 3, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, June 8, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, June 16, 1862
    - from sister-in-law, Mary M. Southall, June 20, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, June 24, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, June 29, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, July 4, 1862
    - from daughter, Selene, and from wife, Elizabeth, July 10-12, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, July 13, 1862
    - from nephew, Randal M. Southall, July 13, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, July 17, 1862
    - from daughter-in-law, Maggie, July 22-27, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, July 24, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, July 27, 1862
    - from sister-in-law, Mary M. Southall, July 30, 1862
    - from nephew, Randal M. Southall, August 4, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, August 5, 1862
    - from sister-in-law, Mary M. Southall, August 14, 1862
    - from Randal M. Ewing, August 17, 1862
    - from servant, Susanna (dictated to Randal M. Ewing), August 25, 1862
    - from Randal M. Ewing, August 28, 1862
    - from wife, Elizabeth, August 29, 1862
    - from W. E. Milton, April 15, (18? )
  - Transcripts – from Incoming Correspondence [selected]
    - April 27, 1862
    - May 2, 1862
    - May 6, 1862
    - May 11, 1862
    - May 15, 1862
    - May 18, 1862 – 2 letters
    - May 21, 1862
    - May 23, 1862
    - May 25, 1862
    - May 26, 1862
    - May 31, 1862
    - June 3, 1862 – 2 letters
    - June 8, 1862
    - June 16, 1862
    - June 20, 1862
    - June 24, 1862
    - June 29, 1862
    - July 4, 1862
    - July 12, 1862
    - July 13, 1862 - 2 letters
    - July 17, 1862
    - July 22, 1862
    - July 24, 1862
    - July 27, 1862
    - July 30, 1862
    - August 5, 1862
    - August 14, 1862
    - August 17, 1862
    - August 25, 1862
    - August 28, 1862
    - August 29, 1862
    - September 24, 1862
    - March 9, 18 – no original letter
  - Transcripts – with footnotes [selected]
    - April 27, 1862
    - May 2, 1862
    - May 8, 1862
    - May 11, 1862
    - May 15, 1862
    - May 18, 1862 – 3 letters
    - May 21, 1862
    - May 23, 1862
    - May 25, 1862
    - May 26, 1862
    - May 31, 1862
    - June 3, 1862
    - June 8, 1862
    - June 16, 1862
    - June 20, 1862
    - June 24, 1862
    - June 29, 1862
    - July 4, 1862
    - July 12, 1862
    - July 13, 1862
    - July 17, 1862
    - July 22, 1862
    - July 24, 1862
    - July 27, 1864
    - July 30, 1862
    - August 4, 1862
    - August 5, 1862
    - August 14, 1862
    - August 17, 1862
    - August 25, 1862
    - September 24, 1862
  - Transcripts – from Incoming Correspondence
    - 2 bound volumes compiled by Alfred Leland Crabb in, April 27, 1862 to September 24, 1862; 1940
- Series III – 2 file folders
  - Photographs
    - Carter, Susanna McGavock ‘Mammy’ (1) Unidentified (1)